<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><author>Turnbull, Gavin,</author><title>Elegy VII. The Dean.</title>, in
                  <title>Poetical Essays,</title> (<pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>, <date>1788</date>),
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="23" to="28">23-28</biblScope>.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head rend="center"><title type="main">Elegy VII. The Dean.<emph rend="super"
                  >1, </emph><note type="head" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">1</emph> First
                  published in <emph rend="italic">Poetical Essays</emph> (1788), pp. 23-28.</note><emph
                  rend="super">2</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">2</emph>
                   [GT's note: The seat of the late unfortunate Earl of Kilmarnock.] Seat of the Boyd
                  family, the Dean, known until 1700 as Kilmarnock Castle, and now as Dean Castle,
                  is just north of the Kilmarnock town centre. The 4th Earl of Kilmarnock, William
                  Boyd (1705-1746) joined the Jacobite rising in 1745 only after Charles Edward
                  Stuart visited Callendar House, part of his wife’s inheritance. Convicted of
                  treason, Boyd was beheaded August 18, 1746 on Tower Hill, and his estates
                  forfeited. His eldest son, James, Lord Boyd, regained the estate in 1751.
               </note></title></head>



         <epigraph rend="center">
            <l><emph rend="italic">The mould’ring walls confess their beauty past,</emph></l>
            <l><emph rend="italic">A fragment falls with each revolving blast.</emph>
            </l>

            <bibl>M<emph rend="super">c</emph>Pherson.<emph rend="super">3</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">3</emph> James Macpherson, <emph rend="italic"
                     >The Highlander; A Poem: in Six Cantos</emph> (1758), p. 59. Turnbull substituted
                  “revolving blast” for “invading blast.”</note></bibl>
         </epigraph>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="1">
            <head rend="center">I.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, in the western main, the sun descends,</l>
               <l rend="indent">And gold’n clouds the low horizon bound,</l>
               <l>The solemn night her sable robe extends,</l>
               <l rend="indent">And nature lies in silence hush’d around. </l>
            </lg>

         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="2">
            <head rend="center">II.</head>

            <lg>
               <l n="5">The lonely shepherd leaves the breezy hill,</l>
               <l rend="indent">And seeks the cottage to indulge repose,</l>
               <l> The lover wanders by the winding rill,</l>
               <l rend="indent">To vent the mournful story of his woes.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="3">
            <head rend="center">III.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Pale Luna gilds the plains and shady bow’rs,</l>
               <l n="10" rend="indent">The limpid streams reflect the silver ray,</l>
               <l>Now fairies revel, in the silent hours,</l>
               <l rend="indent">But fly to distant lands, at break of day. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="4">
            <head rend="center">IV.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>The night owl screams from out her lonely bow’r,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Where, all the day, she solitary reigns,</l>
               <l n="15">Whose voice directs me to yon aged tow’r,</l>
               <l rend="indent">To view of ruin’d grandeur the remains. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="5">
            <head rend="center">V.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Ah me! how sad the tott’ring fabric stands,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Who shall preserve it further from decay?</l>
               <l>Ah none! to other Lords belong its lands,</l>
               <l n="20" rend="indent"> The antient name extinct and dy’d away.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="6">
            <head rend="center">VI.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>That antient dome, which once with grandeur grac’d,</l>
               <l rend="indent">And proud magnificence o’erlook’d the plain,</l>
               <l>Its tow’rs and lofty battlements defac’d,</l>
               <l rend="indent">All desolate and ruinous remain. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="7">
            <head rend="center">VII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l n="25">So stands an aged Chief, great in decay,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Forlorn and sunk beneath a load of years;</l>
               <l>Yet, spite of time and locks of silver gray,</l>
               <l rend="indent">His youth majestic from his age appears. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="8">
            <head rend="center">VIII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>The shaggy green her mould’ring walls deface,</l>
               <l n="30" rend="indent">And ivy wreaths her tott’ring turrets bind,</l>
               <l>Impending fragments hang, in airy space,</l>
               <l rend="indent">In dire contention with the raging wind. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="9">
            <head rend="center">IX.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Where yonder stately ash, in verdure clad,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Extends her boughs outo’er the nodding wall,</l>
               <l n="35">There, round the table, gen’rous heroes fed,</l>
               <l rend="indent">While festive mirth resounded through the hall.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="10">
            <head rend="center">X.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Ah! now no heroes those apartments grace,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Nor social mirth to cheer the dreary walls,</l>
               <l> But airy phantoms roam from place to place,</l>
               <l n="40" rend="indent">And hold nocturnal revels in her halls.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="11">
            <head rend="center">XI.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Around the dome the raven and the owl,</l>
               <l rend="indent">The bat and bittern send a dreary cry,</l>
               <l>The whistling winds through hollow caverns howl,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Startling the lonely trav’ller passing by. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="12">
            <head rend="center">XII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l n="45">Her gardens, once delightful to the eye,</l>
               <l rend="indent">With all that art and nature could adorn,</l>
               <l>Now all o’erwhelm’d with prickly brambles lie,</l>
               <l rend="indent">A scene of ruin, dismal land forlorn. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="13">
            <head rend="center">XIII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>No more is heard, within the verdant shade,</l>
               <l n="50" rend="indent">Th’ am’rous youth his secret vows impart,</l>
               <l>In gentlest accents sooth the list’ning maid,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Urge his soft flame, and pour out all the heart. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="14">
            <head rend="center">XIV.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>The Muse who sung, delighted in the groves,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Gay as the bird, that carols on the spray,</l>
               <l n="55">Pensive, amid the dreary scene, she roves</l>
               <l rend="indent">And tunes to elegy the mournful lay.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="15">
            <head rend="center">XV.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>And thou, lorn stream,may’st wail thy mantling bow’rs,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Where birds melodious oft renew’d the song,</l>
               <l>And sadly echo through yon vaulted tow’rs,</l>
               <l n="60" rend="indent">And mourn in consort as thou roll’st along.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="16">
            <head rend="center">XVI.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>The aged oft with grief those ruins view,</l>
               <l rend="indent">While from their bosoms heaves the unbidden sigh,</l>
               <l>Some relicts still their scenes of youth renew,</l>
               <l rend="indent">To stop the gushing tear, in vain they try. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="17">
            <head rend="center">XVII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l n="65">Short is the date of ought the earth can boast,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Time ruins all with his corroding hand,</l>
               <l>The princely palace, rear’d with mighty cost,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Ev’n brazen tow’rs cannot his rage withstand. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="18">
            <head rend="center">XVIII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Where are the cities so well known to fame,</l>
               <l n="70" rend="indent">The pomp of Ilium,<emph rend="super">4</emph><note
                     type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">4</emph> The city of Troy, as in
                     Homer’s <emph rend="italic">Iliad</emph> and Virgil’s <emph rend="italic"
                        >Aeneid</emph>.</note>" once so far renown’d?</l>
               <l>Of Tyrian<emph rend="super">5</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                        rend="super">5</emph> Relating to Tyre, an ancient Phoenician city of
                     extensive commerce.</note> grandeur but remains a name,</l>
               <l rend="indent">And lofty Babel<emph rend="super">6</emph><note type="gloss"
                     place="bottom"><emph rend="super">6</emph> The city of Babylon; as recorded in
                     Genesis 11:1-9, Noah’s descendants migrated from the east, settled in
                     modern-day Iraq and began to build both the city of Babylon and the tower of
                     Babel. God confounded their speech so that they could not understand one
                     another, the tower collapsed, and Babel’s inhabitants were scattered over the
                     earth. </note> tumbl’d to the ground.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="19">
            <head rend="center">XIX.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Ambition, nourisher of mighty wo,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Vainly upborn on pride’s high soaring wings,</l>
               <l n="75">The fatal source whence these disasters flow,</l>
               <l rend="indent">The fall of empires and the fate of Kings.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="20">
            <head rend="center">XX.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>Here might the Muse, in humble strains, be bold</l>
               <l rend="indent">To tell the great, that all the direful spring</l>
               <l>Of this sad mass of ruin they behold,</l>
               <l n="80" rend="indent">Was from r*******n ’gainst a gracious King.<emph rend="super"
                     >7</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">7</emph> George II
                     (1683-1760) reigned from 1727 until his death. In 1745 supporters of the Stuart
                     monarchy sought to depose George in the last of the Jacobite rebellions, led by
                     Charles Edward Stuart, i.e., Bonnie Prince Charlie.</note></l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="21">
            <head rend="center">XXI.</head>

            <lg>
               <l>But she declines, the mournful tale to tell,</l>
               <l rend="indent">Of him who suffer’d in the hapless strife,</l>
               <l>For why? the mournful story’s known too well,</l>
               <l rend="indent">His honour forfeit nor retain’d his life. </l>
            </lg>
         </div1>
         <div1 type="stanza" n="22">
            <head rend="center">XXII.</head>

            <lg>
               <l n="85">Yet shall remembrance oft renew the sigh,</l>
               <l rend="indent">To mourn the man so lov’d and so ador’d;</l>
               <l>And when the curious trav’ller passeth by,</l>
               <l rend="indent">She’ll point the mansion of the hapless Lord.</l>
            </lg>
         </div1>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
