<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><author>Turnbull, Gavin,</author><title>Preface</title>, in <title>Poetical
                  Essays,</title> (<pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>, <date>1788</date>)</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div>
            <head><title>Preface.<emph rend="super">1</emph><note type="head" place="bottom"><emph
                        rend="super">1</emph> Printed in <emph rend="italic">Poetical Essays</emph>
                     (1788), pp. iii-iv.</note></title></head>
            <p>When an Author is conscious of superior talents, and his writings have already
               merited general approbation, he may step boldly forward; and, without apology, claim
               the public attention to his works: but, when one, unknown and unfriended, who can lay
               no claim to superiority of talents, nor the public prepossession in his favour,
               ventures to appear before their tribunal, he has every reason rather to court their
               candour, and indulgence, than to challenge their censure, or to brave their
               criticism.</p>
            <p> The Author of the following Essays, deprived, early in life, by unforeseen
               misfortunes, of the means of pursuing that liberal plan of education he once had a
               prospect of, has not the vanity to imagine they have either that degree of novelty of
               invention, or correctness of versification which will stand the test of rigid
                  criticism;<emph rend="super">2</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">2</emph> Born in Berwickshire to a dyer, Turnbull left school
                  young, working as a carpet-weaver in Kilmarnock before establishing himself as a
                  poet. See Thomas Crichton, “Biographical Sketches of Alexander Wilson,” in <emph
                     rend="italic">The Weaver</emph> [Paisley], 2 (1819); extract reprinted in
                  Paterson, <emph rend="italic">The Contemporaries of Burns</emph> (Edinburgh: Hugh
                  Paton, etc., 1840), pp. 23-24; and Scott, "Introduction" in <emph rend="italic">A Bard
                     Unkend</emph> (Columbia: Scottish Poetry Reprints, 2015), pp. 5-7. Turnbull makes a
                  similar complaint in the preface to <emph rend="italic">Poems</emph>
                  (1794).</note> the truth is, that their present appearance has been less owing to
               choice than the solicitation of friendship,<emph rend="super">3</emph><note
                  type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">3</emph> Turnbull knew Burns as
                  well as those in Burns’s literary circle, such as David Sillar, from his
                  Kilmarnock days. In addition to encouraging Turnbull, Burns sold at least six
                  subscriptions of <emph rend="italic">Poetical Essays</emph> on Turnbull’s behalf; in a May 1789 letter, Burns
                  enquires about Turnbull's whereabouts so that he could forward him the money. See
                  G. Ross Roy, <emph rend="italic">Letters of Burns</emph> 2nd ed., vol. 1 (Oxford:
                  Clarendon Press, 1985), pp. 399, 413-414; Paterson, <emph
                     rend="italic">The Contemporaries of Burns</emph> (Edinburgh: Hugh Paton, etc.,
                  1840), pp. 92-112; and Scott, “Whatever Happened to Gavin Turnbull” (<emph
                     rend="italic">Robert Burns Lives!</emph>.159 [2012]) as well as <emph
                     rend="italic">A Bard Unkend</emph> (Columbia: Scottish Poetry Reprints, 2015), p. 8.</note>
               ever ready to overlook those faults which will be easily perceived, where the same
               partiality is wanting.</p>
            <p> A number of the Poems in this volume are of the Elegiac, and melancholy kind:
               whether, from natural complexion, or by too much brooding over the failure of his
               once better prospects, the Author acknowledges a partiality for this kind of poetry:
               he has endeavoured to diversify the subjects and the expression; but, after all, the
               same ideas may too frequently occur; and some unfavourable circumstances in his
               situation, by hastening the publication, has prevented them from receiving that
               degree of correction, they would otherwise have obtained.</p>
            <p> On the whole, he submits these juvenile pieces (wrote merely for his own amusement)
               to the public inspection, with much diffidence; and with this hope, That if they have
               any merit worthy of notice, it may in some measure atone for their faults; and,
               should they receive with favour, this, his first attempt, he may perhaps have it in
               his power to pursue those studies which may enable him to produce something more
               worthy of their approbation.</p>
            <p> To his Subscribers, and in particular those who have interested themselves in his
               cause, he returns his most grateful acknowledgment, and assures them it is a favour
               he will always have in remembrance.</p>
            <dateline>Glasgow, <date when="1788-10-24">Oct. 24, 1788</date>.</dateline>
         </div>
      </front>

      <body>
         <p/>
      </body>

   </text>
</TEI>
