<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><author>Turnbull, Gavin,</author><title>Prologue to a Pantomimical Piece. Called
                  the Embakation.</title>, in <title>Poems,</title> (<pubPlace>Dumfries</pubPlace>,
                  <date>1794</date>), <biblScope unit="page" from="8" to="10"
               >8-10</biblScope>.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head><title type="main" rend="center">Prologue to a Pantomimical Piece. Called The
                  Embakation. Perfromed in the Royal Circus, 1739.<emph rend="super">1</emph><note type="head" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">1</emph> First published in <emph rend="italic">Poems</emph>
                  (1794), pp. 8-10. Misprint in title, “Embakation” in the 1794 text, page 8, was
                  corrected by Turnbull to read “Embarkation” in the 1794 Errata, page 48. The
                  pantomime for which this appears to be a prologue is not traceable in, e.g., <emph
                     rend="italic">The London Stage 1660-1800</emph>, or <emph rend="italic">Annals
                     of the Edinburgh Stage</emph>. The Royal Circus named in the title was likely
                  the Edinburgh Equestrian Circus, opened in 1790 in Leith Walk, at which burlettas,
                  pantomimes and equestrian performances were the chief attractions. Alternatively,
                  it might be the Royal Circus of London, though there is no other evidence of
                  Turnbull working in London. Renamed the Surrey Theater in 1806, London’s Circus
                  opened its doors on November 4, 1782 in Blackfriars Road, London and closed in
                  1824.</note></title></head>
         

         <lg type="stanza">
            <l>Since the creation many a mournful scene,</l>
            <l>And fatal tragedy has acted been;</l>
            <l>Though oft the warlike states of Rome and Greece</l>
            <l>Have witness’d many a horrid bloody piece;</l>
            <l n="5">Though tyrants bled, and slaves by them were free’d,</l>
            <l>They never equall’d France’s regicide;<emph rend="super">2</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">2</emph> The Jacobin Maximilian Robespierre
                  (1758-1794) played a major role when the French National Convention voted in
                  January 1793 to execute Louis XVI, and he subsequently led the Committee of Public
                  Safety in its Reign of Terror of 1793-1794. He was himself guillotined without
                  trial on July 28, 1794. </note></l>
            <l>An act which men unborn shall trembling hear,</l>
            <l>And draw from hardest hearts soft pity’s tear!</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent">Though war we dread, who can unpleas’d survey</l>
            <l n="10">All Europe rushing forward to the fray?</l>
            <l>To meet the hell-inspired murd’ring train,</l>
            <l>And offer sacrifices to the slain;</l>
            <l>To plunge in Gallic blood th’ avenging blade,</l>
            <l>And lay the wrath of Louis’<emph rend="super">3</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">3</emph> Louis XVI.</note> injur’d shade.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza">
            <l n="15" rend="indent">Britannia’s Genius, to whose hand is given</l>
            <l>The first and noblest attributes of heav’n;</l>
            <l>Justice and Mercy, calls her sons to arms,</l>
            <l>To arbitrate, and rectify those harms.</l>
            <l>Rous’d by the trumpet and the warlike drum,</l>
            <l n="20"> Spontaneous at the call her heroes come:</l>
            <l> The sprightly youths, whose downy chins presage</l>
            <l>Their forward courage riper than their age,</l>
            <l>Renounce their weeping mother’s tender care,</l>
            <l>Eager the glories of the cause to share;</l>
            <l n="25">The brawny peasant leaves his plow and spade,</l>
            <l>And quits his labour for a nobler trade;</l>
            <l>The smart mechanic throws his tools aside,</l>
            <l>And bears the musket with becoming pride;</l>
            <l>Whist, those whose fortunes more indulgent breed</l>
            <l n="30">In ease and elegance, our numbers lead.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent">Fair dawns the day, auspicious are the gales,</l>
            <l>The hardy seamen hoist the swelling sails;</l>
            <l>And thousands crowd on Belgia’s<emph rend="super">4</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">4</emph> Dutch, for Belgium; in February 1793,
                  the Duke of York, accompanied by 1500 troops, was sent to the Netherlands with the
                  aim of driving out the French and marching on Paris.</note> level strand</l>
            <l>To see the flow’r of Britain’s army land;</l>
            <l n="35"> Rejoicing that their foes<emph rend="super">5</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">5</emph> The French Republic.</note> shall
               quickly yield</l>
            <l> When York’s brave Duke<emph rend="super">6</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"
                     ><emph rend="super">6</emph> Prince Frederick (1763-1827), second son of King
                  George III.</note> advances to the field.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza">
            <l rend="indent">The Muse anticipates the happy times,</l>
            <l>When France shall with aborrence view her crimes;</l>
            <l>When Peace and Reason shall resume their reign,</l>
            <l n="40">And Liberty an equal right maintain;</l>
            <l>When Justice shall avenge a Monarch’s wrongs,</l>
            <l>And teach the duty that to Kings belongs!</l>
         </lg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
