<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?_xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl><author>Turnbull, Gavin,</author><title>Irvine Water. A Poem.</title>, in
                  <title>Poetical Essays,</title> (<pubPlace>Glasgow</pubPlace>, <date>1788</date>),
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="121" to="131">121-131</biblScope>.</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>

         <head rend="center"><title type="main">Irvine Water. A Poem.<emph rend="super"
                  >1</emph><note type="head" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">1</emph> First
                  published in <emph rend="italic">Poetical Essays</emph> (1788), pp. 121-131.
               </note></title></head>
         <epigraph rend="center">
            <l><emph rend="italic">Yet run for ever by the Muse’s skill,</emph></l>
            <l><emph rend="italic">And in the smooth description murmur still.</emph></l>
         </epigraph>
         <bibl rend="center">Addison.<emph rend="super">2</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"
                  ><emph rend="super">2</emph> Joseph Addison, <emph rend="italic">A Letter from
                  Italy</emph> (1701), ll. 48-49 and 79-80.</note></bibl>

         <lg type="stanza" n="1">
            <l>Rous’d at the prospect of the blooming spring,</l>
            <l>Again my youthful Muse attempts to sing:</l>
            <l>Of woods and plains, the beauties to rehearse,</l>
            <l>Or make some fav’rite stream adorn my verse.</l>
         </lg>
         <lg type="stanza" n="2">
            <l n="5" rend="indent">Hail, Irvine,<emph rend="super">3</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">3</emph> The river Irvine flows through
                  southwest Scotland, running near Kilmarnock, down to the coastal town of the same
                  name. Turnbull devoted two other poems to Irvine in <emph rend="italic">Poetical
                     Essays</emph> (1788): “Elegy IV" and “Ode VII: To Irvine Water.” </note> thou
               whose flow’ry banks so gay,</l>
            <l>And vocal groves first heard my rural lay;</l>
            <l>Fain would the Muse this early tribute bring,</l>
            <l>And try the beauties of thy course to sing:</l>
            <l>Ye Naiades,<emph rend="super">4</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">4</emph> Water nymphs.</note> pour your liquid stores along,</l>
            <l n="10">And sweetly murmur to the rural song.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="3">
            <l rend="indent">In vain we search for Simois’ silver source,<emph rend="super"
                  >5</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">5</emph> River of
                  the Trojan plain and, in Greek mythology, name of its God.</note></l>
            <l>Where Ilium’s ruins<emph rend="super">6</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">6</emph> Ancient city of Troy located near the river
                  Scamander.</note> choke its winding course.</l>
            <l>No more Scammander<emph rend="super">7</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">7</emph> In Greek mythology, Scammander, a personification of the
                  river flowing from Mount Ida, sided with the Trojans after Achilles insulted him.
               </note> rages o’er the plains,</l>
            <l>Yet rolls his waves in Homer’s matchless strains.</l>
            <l n="15">O, did my Muse, with equal ardour glow,</l>
            <l>As long thy waves should in my numbers flow.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="4">
            <l rend="indent">Now dawns the day, the dusky shadows fly,</l>
            <l>The sun in glory mounts the azure sky,</l>
            <l>The distant landscape opens to the view,</l>
            <l n="20">The misty mountains, wet with early dew,</l>
            <l>Round pearly drops hang pendant on the spray,</l>
            <l>The flow’rs expand their foliage to the day,</l>
            <l>On ev’ry verdant bush and blooming thorn,</l>
            <l>The plumy warblers hail the rosy morn.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="5">
            <l n="25" rend="indent">What joy to wander undisturb’d with care,</l>
            <l>To breathe the fragrance of the morning air,</l>
            <l>Where Irvine’s streams glide gently through the dale,</l>
            <l>And gather health from ev’ry rising gale;</l>
            <l>To stray the woods and dewy lawns among,</l>
            <l n="30">Led by the Muse, to meditate the song,</l>
            <l>Or curious, wand’ring to an airy height,</l>
            <l>Indulge my fancy with the varied sight.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="6">
            <l rend="indent">From where yon mountain’s tufted tops arise,</l>
            <l>To where the sun rolls down the western skies,</l>
            <l n="35">Where, midst a spacious frith,<emph rend="super">8</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">8</emph>
                  <emph rend="italic">n.</emph> inlet of the sea.</note> black Arran<emph
                  rend="super">9</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">9</emph>
                  Largest island in the Firth of Clyde, visible from the Ayrshire coast.</note>
               shrouds</l>
            <l>Its rocky top, among surrounding clouds,</l>
            <l>A noble prospect, stretch’d before the eye,</l>
            <l>May with Hesperia<emph rend="super">10</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">10</emph> Poetic name for Italy or Spain.</note> or Arcadia<emph
                  rend="super">11</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super"
                     >11</emph> Mountainous district in Greece; in literature, an ideal, rustic
                  setting.</note> vie</l>
            <l>Here, winding dales, and lenthen’d plains extend,</l>
            <l n="40">There, from the vales, the cloud capt hills ascend;</l>
            <l>Here, waving forests, mantl’d all in green,</l>
            <l>With fertile fields and flow’ry lawns between;</l>
            <l>There, winding streams the verdant meads adorn,</l>
            <l>And, dimpling smooth, reflect the rays of morn.</l>
            <l n="45">Along the margin rural seats appear,</l>
            <l>And gardens blooming with the vernal year.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="7">
            <l rend="indent">What though the wond’ring trav’ller still admires,</l>
            <l>Italia’s lofty domes and lengthen’d spires;</l>
            <l>Her gilded prospects, stretch’d in bright array,</l>
            <l n="50">Poetic scenes with flow’rs and verdure gay,</l>
            <l>Or let Arabia boast her spicy fields,</l>
            <l>More precious blessings Caledonia<emph rend="super">12</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">12</emph> Literary name for Scotland, formerly a
                  Roman term for the region.</note> yields;</l>
            <l>Though less exuberant, our northern soil,</l>
            <l>Yet peace and plenty crown the lab’rers toil;</l>
            <l n="55">Here all that’s charming, all that’s sweet is found,</l>
            <l>And Liberty makes nature smile around.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="8">
            <l rend="indent">Where first the stream his sacred source forsakes,</l>
            <l>And, through the wilds, his mazy winding takes;</l>
            <l>Where water, from the pendant rock, distills,</l>
            <l n="60">And, foster’d by the gently purling rills,</l>
            <l>Where circling ivy mantling bow’rs display,</l>
            <l>The lonely owl forsakes the cheerful day.</l>
            <l>Here, like some ruffian from the world exil’d,</l>
            <l>The rav’nous hawk reigns tyrant of the wild;</l>
            <l n="65">The lonely shepherd, on the banks reclin’d,</l>
            <l>Nurses fantastic notions in his mind.</l>
            <l>The turtle wails, upon the aged trees,</l>
            <l>The water, sounding to the whisp’ring breeze,</l>
            <l>Repeating caves resound the water’s fall,</l>
            <l n="70">And melancholy murmurs answer all.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="9">
            <l rend="indent">As by degrees the Naiades swell the tide,</l>
            <l>Th’ expanding landscape opens fair and wide;</l>
            <l>There stately towns and villages arise,</l>
            <l>And lofty piles, whose turrets reach the skies,</l>
            <l n="75">Here many an antient tow’r and fortress stands,</l>
            <l>The sad memorials of contending lands;</l>
            <l>When kindred nations fiercely strove in arms,</l>
            <l>And fill’d the hostile land with dire alarms:</l>
            <l>Then heap’d with slaughter ev’ry field appear’d,</l>
            <l n="80">And war through all the land his horrid aspect rear’d.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="10">
            <l rend="indent">Where heaps of carnage strew’d th’ ensanguin’d plain,</l>
            <l>The skilful farmer rears the yellow grain:</l>
            <l>The lazy shepherd lies upon the ground,</l>
            <l>Amid th’ extended trench, and verdant mound;</l>
            <l n="85">While rough industry plies his useful hand,</l>
            <l>And fills with plenty all the peaceful land.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="11">
            <l rend="indent">Along the level holms, with verdure gay,</l>
            <l>The patient angler slowly bends his way,</l>
            <l>With taper rod, and well dissembled-hook,</l>
            <l n="90">To tempt the thoughtless tenants of the brook.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="12">
            <l rend="indent">Where in the dimpling pool the shepherd spies,</l>
            <l>Th’ inverted landscape and the liquid skies,</l>
            <l>The youths with naked arms the waves divide,</l>
            <l>And smoothly cleave, along the yielding tide.</l>
            <l n="95">But let each forward heedless youth beware,</l>
            <l>Nor the sad fate of young Menalcas<emph rend="super">13</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">13</emph> Shepherd or rustic figuring in
                  Virgil’s <emph rend="italic">Eclogues</emph> and Theocritus’s <emph rend="italic"
                     >Idyls</emph>. Centered on the shepherd-poet’s desire to achieve worldly fame
                  through poetry, <emph rend="italic">Eclogue</emph> 5 tells the tale of Menalcas
                  and Mopsus who mourn their deceased companion, Daphnis.</note> share;</l>
            <l>Who, urg’d by fervent heat, his limbs to cool,</l>
            <l>Impatient plung’d amid the sullen pool:</l>
            <l>Eager he strives, his efforts all are vain,</l>
            <l n="100">Him fate denies the distant shore to gain,</l>
            <l>The whirling eddies curl above his head,</l>
            <l>The lovely youth is number’d with the dead.</l>
            <l>Much was the grief his frantic mother bore,</l>
            <l>His aged father much, his sweetheart more;</l>
            <l n="105">Whom love with chains of strong affection bound,</l>
            <l>And soon the nuptial tie their bliss had crown’d,</l>
            <l>But fates malignant ’gainst their joy conspir’d,</l>
            <l>And, all at once, their pleasing hopes retir’d.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="13">
            <l rend="indent">Now wouldst thou sing what noble feats appear,</l>
            <l n="110">What antient heroes form’d their dwellings here,</l>
            <l>The tow’rs of Loudon<emph rend="super">14</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"
                     ><emph rend="super">14</emph> Located in Ayrshire, Loudon Castle is one of the
                  oldest family seats in Scotland. Paterson comments that Loudon was the “seat of
                  the Dowager-Marchioness of Hastings, daughter of James-Mure Campbell, fifth Earl
                  of Loudoun, who died in 1786” (<emph rend="italic">Contemporaries of Burns</emph>,
                  Edinburgh: Hugh Paton, etc., 1840, p. 102).</note> first salute the eye</l>
            <l>With lofty walls, and turrets rear’d on high;</l>
            <l>Gay to the view, upon a rising ground,</l>
            <l>With pendant woods and shady bow’rs around.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="14">
            <l n="115" rend="indent">All hail, ye solemn thought-inspiring groves,</l>
            <l>Where rapt entranc’d, sweet contemplation roves,</l>
            <l>Where charming fancy leads her airy train,</l>
            <l>Who touch the Muses’ lyre or breathe th’ enamour’d strain.</l>
            <l>For there the lover, led by Cynthia’s<emph rend="super">15</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">15</emph> Feminine name derived from Mount
                  Cythus of Delos island on which the Greek goddess of the moon, Artemis was born.
               </note> ray,</l>
            <l n="120">Along the river’s margin winds his way;</l>
            <l>Or pensive, seated ’neath the spreading boughs,</l>
            <l>Breathes, to the lonely woods, his am’rous vows;</l>
            <l>While fairies, form their nightly cavalcades,</l>
            <l>And hold gay revels in the moonlight shades,</l>
            <l n="125">Aerial minstrels swell the soothing strain,</l>
            <l>And heav’nly airs enchant the list’ning swain.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="15">
            <l rend="indent">See where the Dean<emph rend="super">16</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">16</emph> Seat of the Boyd family, the Dean,
                  known until 1700 as Kilmarnock Castle, is situated in Kilmarnock’s modern-day Dean
                  Castle Country Park. The 4<emph rend="super">th</emph> Earl of Kilmarnock, William
                  Boyd, participated in the Jacobite uprising of 1715 and 1745 which resulted in his
                  execution and loss of estates in 1746. His eldest son, James, Lord Boyd, regained
                  the estate in 1751.</note> her ruin’d fabric rears,</l>
            <l> A mournful scene, her naked wall appears,</l>
            <l>The clasping ivy shades her tott’ring tow’rs,</l>
            <l n="130">Where night-owls form their melancholy bow’rs,</l>
            <l>Prone from the top, huge ruin’d fragments fall,</l>
            <l>The howling wind sounds dreary in the hall,</l>
            <l>No more the voice of mirth is heard to sound,</l>
            <l>But melancholy silence reigns around.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="16">
            <l rend="indent" n="135">Where late, an antiquated pile appear’d</l>
            <l>In days of yore, by Gothic artists rear’d,</l>
            <l>Upon the margin of the rolling tide,</l>
            <l>Stands Caprington, of Coila’s tow’rs<emph rend="super">17</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">17</emph> Located in Ayrshire, Caprington castle
                  dates from the 15th century and was remodeled in 1780. As noted by Paterson, in
                  1788 it was the seat of John Smith Cuninghame, Esq. (<emph rend="italic"
                     >Contemporaries of Burns</emph>, Edinburgh: Hugh Paton, etc., 1840,
                  p. 103).</note> the pride,</l>
            <l>Which with superior majesty appears</l>
            <l n="140">The tedious labour of revolving years,</l>
            <l>Its ample walls bespeak its master’s mind,</l>
            <l>Industry’s friend, benevolent and kind.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="17">
            <l rend="indent"> What verse, O Fairly,<emph rend="super">18</emph><note type="gloss"
                  place="bottom"><emph rend="super">18</emph> Reference to the residence of Sir John
                  Cuninghame Fairlie, Bart. (Paterson, <emph rend="italic">Contemporaries of
                     Burns</emph>, Edinburgh: Hugh Paton, etc., 1840, p. 103).</note> can thy halls
               depaint,</l>
            <l>And stately portico of vast extent,</l>
            <l n="145">Design’d with taste, and execute with cost,</l>
            <l>Nor can the neighb’ring seats such beauty boast.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="18">
            <l rend="indent">High on a mound Dundonald’s ruin<emph rend="super">19</emph><note
                  type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph rend="super">19</emph> Ancient residence of the
                  Cochranes of Dundonald (Paterson, <emph rend="italic">Contemporaries of
                     Burns</emph>, Edinburgh: Hugh Paton, etc., 1840, p. 103).</note> stands,</l>
            <l>And of the frith a prospect wide commands,</l>
            <l>Where Arran rears aloft its sable brow,</l>
            <l n="150">And frowns terrific on the waves below.</l>
            <l>Ailsey’s round steril rock<emph rend="super">20<note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                        rend="super">20</emph> Ailsa Craig; prominent rocky islet in the firth of
                     Clyde, visible from the Ayrshire Coast and, during the Scottish Reformation, a
                     haven for Catholics.</note></emph> the prospect ends,</l>
            <l>Whose airy peak among the clouds ascends,</l>
            <l>Fair Irvine, on the sandy margin plac’d,</l>
            <l>Appears with lofty spires and turrets grac’d,</l>
            <l n="155">The swelling surges beat against the shore,</l>
            <l>And ’mongst the rocky isles tempestuous roar,</l>
            <l>The stately vessels, on the foaming tide,</l>
            <l>Loaded with wealth, along the billows ride;</l>
            <l>I see the crowded masts, and swelling sails,</l>
            <l n="160">The waving streamers, flying in the gales,</l>
            <l>And gaze with wonder, on the splendid show,</l>
            <l>Of lofty towns and busy crowds below.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="19">
            <l rend="indent">Hold, hold my Muse, at once suspend thy flight,</l>
            <l>And look enamour’d from this airy height,</l>
            <l n="165">Where stands secure, upon the river’s side,</l>
            <l>A rural dwelling, destitute of pride;</l>
            <l>No costly ornaments the structure grace,</l>
            <l>But simple nature beautifies the place;</l>
            <l>Here Ruricola<emph rend="super">21</emph><note type="gloss" place="bottom"><emph
                     rend="super">21</emph> Latin, a countryman, rustic farmer.</note> dwells, of
               swains the best,</l>
            <l n="170">Of feelings and a gen’rous mind possess’d,</l>
            <l>Improv’d by science, from pedantry free;</l>
            <l>Skill’d in the rules of deep philosophy;</l>
            <l>Of plants the aromatic virtue knows,</l>
            <l>And on his garden ev’ry care bestows,</l>
            <l n="175">There trims his flow’rs, or prunes th’ encumber’d trees,</l>
            <l>Or forms a proper station for his bees;</l>
            <l>Curious, their balmy labours to survey,</l>
            <l>Delightful task to pass the shining hours away.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="20">
            <l rend="indent">O gentle swain, how happy could I spend</l>
            <l n="180">This fleeting life with such a gen’rous friend,</l>
            <l>Well pleas’d, my tuneful labours to pursue,</l>
            <l>Improv’d by charming solitude and you.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="21">
            <l rend="indent">That man how bless’d, who prudently retires,</l>
            <l>Nor to be great and arrogant aspires;</l>
            <l n="185">Content alone, with what his fortune gives,</l>
            <l>To strife unknown, he independent lives:</l>
            <l>What though no cringing flatt’rers at his gate</l>
            <l>Stand trembling, and at awful distance wait,</l>
            <l>Though no obsequious minions call him Lord,</l>
            <l n="190">Nor cates luxurious heap his humble board,</l>
            <l>Nor costly ornaments his dwelling hold,</l>
            <l>Nor chests encumber’d with imprison’d gold,</l>
            <l>Yet his the life from expectation free,</l>
            <l>Corroding care and vain anxiety:</l>
            <l n="195">Peace stands a centinel to guard his door,</l>
            <l>And keep at distance each malignant pow’r;</l>
            <l>Time flies for him, on softest silken wings,</l>
            <l>And each revolving day contentment brings:</l>
            <l>With joy he breathes the balmy gales of morn,</l>
            <l n="200">And sees the night a welcome guest return:</l>
            <l>’Tis his to wander o’er the fertile fields,</l>
            <l>And taste what nature uncorrupted yields;</l>
            <l>Her laws to study and her works explore,</l>
            <l>And on the wings of contemplation soar:</l>
            <l n="205">Throughout the whole, to trace the gradual line</l>
            <l>Which leads progressive to the source divine,</l>
            <l>To teach the soul above the earth t’ ascend,</l>
            <l>To weigh his dust and meditate his end.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="22">
            <l rend="indent">Let others toil assiduously for fame,</l>
            <l n="210">Contend for honour, and a deathless name:</l>
            <l>All vain applause, and honour I’d resign;</l>
            <l>Give me a friend, and such a life be mine.</l>
         </lg>

         <lg type="stanza" n="23">
            <l rend="indent">Thus, when the summer’s joys could scarce delight,</l>
            <l>Or grove or stream my weary steps invite;</l>
            <l n="215">I try’d the Muse, beneath the shade reclin’d,</l>
            <l>To ease a pensive melancholy mind,</l>
            <l>To sooth my fancy with the scenes that please,</l>
            <l>Rural contentment, and poetic ease. </l>
         </lg>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
